Indiana University Bloomington Professional Council records, 1980-1998 C210
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University Bloomington Professional Council records
1980-1998
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University, Bloomington. Bloomington Professional Council
C210
3 cubic feet
The Indiana University Bloomington Professional Staff Council became an official university organization on October 16, 1985. This representative council was created to empower the many professional staff members at the university by giving them a voice in university policies and actions that affect the working conditions, services, and benefits of their employment. The bulk of the collection consists of meeting minutes as well as information concerning the many committees, task forces, and university organizations that affect the daily operations and policies of the Professional Staff Council.
Access Restrictions
Indicated files are restricted. Consult Archives staff for further information.
Advance notice is required for access.
Administrative History
The Indiana University Bloomington Professional Staff Council became an official university organization when it's Constitution and Bylaws were approved by university administration on October 16, 1985. This representative council was created to empower the many professional staff members at the university by giving them a voice in university policies and actions that affected the working conditions and services/benefits of their employment. Before the approval of the Council's governing laws, it was a petition circulated by a representation committee appointed by the university administration, endorsed by the university's professional employees, and later presented to the IU Board of Trustees by an ad hoc group of four professional employees that laid the groundwork for the creation of the Council. Prior to the creation of the Council, many of the university's professional staff members were members or active participants in a non-officially-sanctioned group called the Indiana University Professional Staff Association. The IUPSA was formed in 1983 as a forum for the concerns and opinions of the university professional staff members on the Bloomington campus. This association was later disbanded in 1988 in favor of the Council.
The IUB Professional Staff Council held their first meeting on May 14, 1986 as a group of 24 professional staff members elected from 10 electoral units (now 21 professional staff members elected from 7 units) representing a balanced population of the university's professional community. In it's early years the Council worked to establish productive relations with university administration. The first issues of concern for this new university organization were the status of retirement plans, health care concerns, and issues concerning the job security of many professional staff members. The Council's first president, Don Brinneman, and other executive officers were successful in gaining the attention of many members of the university administration including that of it's president, John Ryan. Since these first connections were made, many subsequent members of the university administration have actively interacted with the Council even going so far as attending their meetings often as speakers.
The Indiana University Professional Staff Constitution begins with an official description of what the university considers a professional staff member; an individual appointed at 50% or full-time employment status as coded by the university budget. Professional Staff Members are represented by 21 professional staff members comprising the Professional Staff Council. The elected members of the Council are responsible for providing their fellow staff members with a means of making informed decisions and engaging in active participation regarding any university action or policy that would effect the university's professional community. The Council is responsible for dictating the concerns of the university's professional staff through questionnaires, surveys, meetings, and other forms of interaction and presenting them as formal proposals to the university Vice-President for Administration. The Council is required to meet once a month in which such meetings are open to non-members. In terms of responsibility, the Council is required to report its decisions and other proceedings to the members of the professional staff and these reports are also required to state how each Council member or his/her proxy voted on important issues. In terms of the Council's administration, the Council's Executive committee is required to elect a President, Vice-President, Secretary, Treasurer, and Parliamentarian. Each Council member is required, as a minimum, to serve a three-year term with the possibility of serving another consecutive term after which they are ineligible to serve for the next two elections. The Bylaws state that 1/3 of the Council's members are required to run for re-election each year. After amendments to the Professional Staff Council Constitution have been discussed by the Council, such amendments must be approved by a 2/3 majority vote of the Council before being distributed by a mail ballot to the Professional Staff Association. A minimum of a 33% vote by the Professional Staff Association in favor of adopting the amendment is necessary before the newly ratified amendment is submitted to the IU Board of Trustees.
As mentioned above, the Council's first president, Don Brinneman, was a very influential executive member of the IUBPSC as was Doris-Jean Burton, the Council's first Vice President, who addressed the Faculty Affairs committee of the IU Board of Trustees concerning the establishment of the IUBPSC. The duties of both offices are extensive and require active cooperation with the many divisions and members of the Council. The President is responsible for chairing Council meetings, referring matters to the separate committees, preparing written annual reports, representing the Council at Bloomington Faculty Council meetings, and selecting the chairs of Standing committees and Ad Hoc task forces amongst other responsibilities. The Vice President is responsible for being the contact person for other university employee organizations or campus group; chairing a committee responsible for the Council's presentations to the IU Board of Trustees; as well as assuming the responsibilities of the President in his/her absence.
Each Council member is required to serve on at least one Standing committee each year. Attendance at each of the committee's monthly meetings is required. Each Standing committee is chaired by an individual appointed by the Council's president. The chairs of these committees are responsible for delegating assignments to the separate committee members, scheduling committee meetings, setting the agenda for committee meetings, and preparing written reports to the university's professional staff amongst other responsibilities. The Executive committee of the IUBPSC has the responsibility of establishing ad hoc committees and task forces to research staff related issues and report their findings to the Council. Like the standing committees, the ad hoc committees and task forces are chaired by individuals appointed by the Council's president who creates written reports for the Council, but attendance is not as strictly regulated since such groups meet only when necessary, and may only be active for a short duration.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series, Administration, Committees, taskforces, and university organizations, and Membership.
Scope and Content Note
The majority of this collection is comprised of the Indiana University-Bloomington Professional Staff Council Business meeting minutes (the bulk falling in-between the years 1993 and 1997) as well as information concerning the many committees, task forces, and university organizations that effected the daily operations and policies of the Professional Staff Council. The collection also contains an Administration series with sub-series concerning the Professional Staff Council's President, & Vice-President; a Membership series comprised of membership lists and election information; and a Committees/Task Forces/University Organizations series with a sub-series containing meeting(s) information and minutes of the separate committees, task forces, and university organizations. Besides bearing the official title of the Indiana University-Bloomington Professional Staff Council some people refer to this professional organization as the Bloomington Professional Staff Council, the Bloomington Professional Council (most common throughout the collection), the Professional Council, or, in very informal instances, just as "the Council".
The Administration series contains documents regarding the bodies that govern the actions and policies of the Professional Staff Council. The IU Board of Trustees as well as individuals such as university Chancellor and Vice-President for academic affairs Kenneth R. R. Gros Louis and university President Myles Brand are represented here. Also in this series are the many university policies and financial summaries/budgets that have had effect on the university's professional employees. Three documents within the Administration series (IUB Staff Council & IU Professional Staff Association Bylaws; IUBPSC Constitution; & the Constitution of the Bloomington faculty) are closely related in that they have evolved and been amended in response to professional employee related issues since the formation of the Professional Staff Council with each file containing drafts and variations of the separate documents. In many cases the Bylaws, Constitution, and Resolutions of the Professional Staff Council are also contained in the IUBPSC Meetings & Minutes series as well as certain committee(s) minutes by their corresponding year. The many drafts of the IUBPSC Constitution also contain variations of the committee's bylaws. The Vice-President and President sub-series contain individual correspondence and reports of both officers. In most cases the reports and significant pieces of correspondence by the Professional Staff Council's Vice-President and President are also contained in the corresponding IUBPSC Meetings & Minutes.
The Committees/Task Forces/University Organizations series contains individual correspondence, committee reports, and other documents related to the issues for which each body is responsible. There are also many ad hoc committees, task forces, and study groups of brief existence depending upon the resolution, or lack thereof, of whatever university policy or action happened to concern the university's professional employees. There are committees of the Professional Staff Council that were created in the early years of the Council's existence and are still active today, such as the Communications, Salary & Benefits, Nominations & Elections, and other committees. In some cases, the committees and task forces represented in this series were actually created by the Bloomington Faculty Council with professional employees serving as active members amongst university faculty in these groups. This series also contains a sub-series titled Committee Meetings & Minutes which includes the minutes of the IUB Professional Staff Council Business meeting as well as the minutes of separate committees, task forces, and university organizations. Often included in the IUB Professional Staff Council's minutes are the monthly and year end reports of the separate committees within the Council as well as reports by the Council's Vice-President and President. Over the course of the Council's existence there have been many individuals serving as the Council's Secretary who were responsible for compiling the minutes of the meetings.
The Membership series is comprised of lists of the university's Professional Staff Association and members of the Professional Staff Council as well as the Council's election related information. The membership lists cover the fluctuating professional staff population over the course of the Council's existence as both general listings and lists by electoral units/districts. The documents concerning election information are mainly election results, letters of nomination, ballots, biographical statements of the individuals nominated to the Professional Staff Council, and statements made by the individuals elected to various positions.
Separated Material
Photographs transferred to the University Archives Photographs Collection.
Acquisition Information
Accessions 2002/041, 2000/027, 99/053.
Provenance
Accession 2002/041 transferred by Teresa Spiegel, Bloomington Professional Council.
Accessions 2000/027 and 99/053 transferred by Doris Burton, Political Science.
Universities and colleges --Indiana --Bloomington --Employees.; Universities and colleges --Indiana --Bloomington --Administration.; Management --Employee participation --Indiana --Bloomington.; Employee empowerment --Indiana --Bloomington.; Strategic planning --Employee participation --Indiana --Bloomington.; Indiana University, Bloomington. Bloomington Professional Council -- Archives; Indiana University, Bloomington. Bloomington Professional Council -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University, Bloomington. Bloomington Professional Council -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Indiana University, Bloomington -- Employees
- Administration, 1983-1997
  - Administrative Review, 28 Mar 1991 (Box 1)
  - American Federation of Teachers-IUB, Sep 1983 - Jan/Feb 1987 (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees, Indiana University (Box 1)
    - 1 Jul 1981 - 9 Jan 1991 (Box 1)
    - Presidential Search Committee, Jul 1986 - 17 Sep 1986 (Box 1)
  - Brand, Myles, Indiana/Oregon University President, Fall 1993 - 19 Jan 1995 (Box 1)
  - Constitution of the Bloomington Faculty, undated (Box 1)
  - Gros Louis, Kenneth, Vice-President-IUB, 1986/1987 - 25 Apr 1996 (Box 1)
  - Indiana University Personnel Policies, Jan 1985 - 25 Jan 1996 (Box 1)
  - IUB Staff Council & IU Professional Staff Association Bylaws, 7 Dec 1983 - 22 May 1995 (Box 1)
  - IUB Professional Staff Council (Box 1)
    - Budgets & Financial Summaries, 28 Feb 1994 - 1996 (Box 1)
    - Constitution, 22 Jan 1985 - 1991 (Box 1)
    - Hierarchy, undated (Box 1)
    - History, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Office, 27 Jul 1996 - 14 May 1997 (Box 1)
    - Officers, Duties & Responsibilities, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Resolutions, 10 Dec 1987 - 19 Feb 1996 (Box 1)
  - Job Classification Program for Professional Staff positions of the Indiana University System, Nov 1986 (Box 1)
  - Personnel Policy for Clerical & Technical Staff employees, undated (Box 1)
  - President, 1986-1996
    - IUB Professional Staff Council President (Box 1)
      - Brineman, Don R., 22 May 1986 - 27 Jan 1988 (Box 1)
      - Burton, Doris-Jean, 1 Feb 1988 - 27 Mar 1989 (Box 1)
      - Churchill, Sandra, 25 Mar 1992 - 2 Nov 1992 (Box 1)
      - Foster, Charles (Chuck) C., Jan 1989 - Jun 1991 (Box 1)
      - Rice, Tim, 15 Jan 1996 - 23 Jul 1996 (Box 1)
    - IUB Professional Staff Council President's Reports, 11 Nov 1987 - 18 May 1994 (Box 1)
  - Vice-President, 1986-1993
    - IUB Professional Staff Council Vice President (Box 1)
      - Burton, Doris-Jean, 22 May 1986 - 1 Dec 1987 (Box 1)
      - Foster, Charles (Chuck) C., 26 May 1986 - 28 Mar 1991 (Box 1)
    - IUB Professional Staff Council Vice-President's Reports, 17 Dec 1992 - 19 Nov 1993 (Box 1)
- Committees/Task Forces/University Organizations, 1980-1998
  - Access & Professional Education Groups, 16 May 1988 - 22 Jun 1988 (Box 1)
  - Ad Hoc Committee for the Board of Trustees Retreat, 23 May 1988 - 2 Aug 1988 (Box 1)
  - Ad Hoc Budget Advisory Committee, 22 Oct 1990 (Box 1)
  - Ad Hoc Classification Review Committee, 24 Apr 1995 - 2 Apr 1997 (Box 1)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Creative Solutions to Budget Reductions, Apr 1994 - Aug 1994 (Box 1)
  - Ad Hoc Finance Committee, 11 Jan 1990 (Box 1)
  - Ad Hoc Committee, Salary Increase Petition, 9 Jul 1981 - 9 Nov 1981 (Box 1)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on the Structure of Campus Governance, 8 Apr 1996 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Council Steering Committee, 11 Jun 1986 - 3 Apr 1989 (Box 1)
  - Committee to review the Affirmative Action Office, 16 May 1988 (Box 1)
  - Bloomington Faculty Council, 17 Dec 1981 - 28 Feb 1996 (Box 1)
  - Bloomington Faculty Council Fringe Benefits Committee, 6 Jun 1985 - 2 Feb 1993 (Box 1)
  - IUB Professional Staff Council Breakfast Forum, 28 Nov 1995 - 27 Mar 1996 (Box 1)
  - Budget Advisory Committee, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Budget Affairs Committee, 26 Oct 1987 - 13 Nov 1994 (Box 1)
  - Campus Recreational Sports Committee, 19 Apr 1988 - 16 Sep 1989 (Box 1)
  - Child Care Coalition, 17 Oct 1995 - 9 Apr 1996 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Committees, 1980-1998 (Box 1)
  - Communications Committee, 10 May 1991 - 1994 (Box 1)
  - Competitiveness Task Force, 25 Oct 1993 - Feb 1994 (Box 1)
  - "Computer Users' Privileges and Responsibilities" Subcommittee, 25 Jan 1990 (Box 1)
  - Cost in Higher Education, Report of the Task Force, University of Michigan, Mar 1990 (Box 1)
  - Demographic Subcommittee, 24 Jul 1986 - 5 Sep 1986 (Box 1)
  - Early Retirement Committee, 15 Jan 1991 (Box 1)
  - Early Retirement Plans Study Committee, 14 Feb 1991 - 2 Mar 1991 (Box 1)
  - Early Retirement Task Force, 10 Jun 1991 (Box 1)
  - Educational Grants Committee, 1986 - 14 Jan 1987 (Box 1)
  - Employment Conditions,Task Force on, 1 Jul 1981 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee, 6 Apr 1986 - 1 Dec 1995 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Compensation, Task Force on, 22 Jan 1991 (Box 1)
  - Flex Benefits Program Task Force, Spring 1993 - 10 Nov 1995 (Box 1)
  - Flexible Benefits Task Force, 1993 - 21 Nov 1995 (Box 1)
  - Flex Benefits IUB Professional Staff Council Survey, 7 Nov 1994 - 7 Nov 1995 (Box 1)
  - Fun Frolic Committee, 22 Jul 1988 - 19 Jun 1991 (Box 1)
  - Governmental Relations Committee, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Health Insurance Task Force, 20 May 1988 (Box 1)
  - IPFW Administrative Staff Council, 9 Sep 1988 - 19 May 1989 (Box 1)
  - IUB Professional Staff Council Endowment Campaign, 6 Feb 1996 - 21 Apr 1997 (Box 1)
  - IUB Professional Staff Association, 18 Dec 1984 - 18 Jan 1988 (Box 1)
  - IUB Professional Staff Association Auditing Committee, 30 Oct 1984 - 8 Jan 1986 (Box 1)
  - IUB Professional Staff Association Finance Committee, 30 Oct 1984 (Box 1)
  - IUB Professional Staff Association Program Committee, 30 Oct 1984 (Box 1)
  - IU Health Insurance Plan Reorganization Task Force, 11 Oct 1988 (Box 1)
  - Institutional Committees with Student Representatives, undated (Box 1)
  - Legislative Committee, 17 Feb 1987 - 1991 (Box 1)
  - Legislative Liaison Committee, 4 Aug 1989 - 15 May 1991 (Box 1)
  - Library Professional Council, 27 Nov 1995 - 3 Jan 1996 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Committees & Task Forces, 23 Feb 1988 - 20 Apr 1997 (Box 1)
  - Newsletter Committee, Oct 1984 - Jan 1996 (Box 1)
  - Nominations & Elections Committee, 18 Dec 1985 - 1986 (Box 1)
  - Non-Academic Family Leave Proposal Committee, 4 Oct 1990 (Box 1)
  - Parking Appeals Panel, 17 Oct 1995 (Box 1)
  - Parliamentary Committee, 3 May 1990 - 15 May 1991 (Box 1)
  - Personal Safety Committee, 26 Oct 1987 (Box 1)
  - Phi Beta Kappa of Indiana Chapter, 16 Oct 1987 (Box 1)
  - Professional Affairs Committee, 25 Sep 1984 - 4 Oct 1988 (Box 1)
  - Professional Concerns Committee, 1990 - 8 Mar 1996 (Box 1)
  - Professional Concerns Committee-Evaluation Project, 1982 - 9 Dec 1996 (Box 1)
  - Professional Concerns Committee-Sabbatical Project, Apr 1986 - 18 Nov 1994 (Box 1)
  - Lists of IUB Professional Staff Council Committees & Members, 31 Oct 1984 - 3 Apr 1995 (Box 1)
  - Professional Recognition & Ceremonies Committee, 1 May 1989 - 6 May 1991 (Box 1)
  - Professional Staff Training, Committee on, 18 Feb 1982 - 16 Mar 1982 (Box 1)
  - Proposed Family Leave for IU Staff Employees Committee, 16 Oct 1987 - Apr 1991 (Box 1)
  - Representation Committee, 10 Jan 1980 - 26 Feb 1986 (Box 2)
  - Resources Task Force, 11 Jan 1991 - 18 Jun 1991 (Box 2)
  - Responsibility Centered Management (RCM) Committee, Apr 1995 - 7 Nov 1995 (Box 2)
  - Salary Committee, Nov 1981 - 5 Jan 1988 (Box 2)
  - Salary & Benefits Committee (Box 2)
    - (folder 1 of 2), 24 Mar 1987 - 3 Feb 1993 (Box 2)
    - (folder 2 of 2), 11 Mar 1993 - 4 Mar 1996 (Box 2)
  - SDC Steering Committee, 13 Oct 1995 - 15 May 1996 (Box 2)
  - Search for Dean(s) Committee(s), 2 Feb 1987 - 5 Dec 1988 (Box 2)
  - Space Management Subcommittee, 13 Nov 1989 (Box 2)
  - Staff/Faculty Affairs Committee, 24 Feb 1988 - 29 Mar 1996 (Box 2)
  - Staff Merit Committee, 14 Oct 1986 - 10 Dec 1986 (Box 2)
  - Task Force on University Organization, 6 Jan 1986 (Box 2)
  - Torchinsky Review Committee, Summer 1994 - 10 Jul 1995 (Box 2)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted
  - Transportation & Parking Advisory Committee, 24 Nov 1987 - 9 Aug 1996 (Box 2)
  - University Policies Committee, 28 Mar 1994 - 20 Jan 1996 (Box 2)
  - Meetings & Minutes, 1981-1998
    - Administrative Council Steering Committee, 13 Jan 1987 - 18 May 1989 (Box 2)
    - Affirmative Action Committee, 31 Jul 1986 - 11 Oct 1988 (Box 2)
    - Bloomington Faculty Council, 12 Sep 1995 - 29 Apr 1996 (Box 2)
    - Board of Trustees Staff Affairs Committee, 1 Aug 1988 - 4 Feb 1991 (Box 2)
    - Budgetary Affairs Committee, 24 Nov 1992 (Box 2)
    - Commission on Health Care, 4 Mar 1994 - 7 Feb 1996 (Box 2)
    - Communications Committee, 21 Jul 1986 - 8 Sep 1987 (Box 2)
    - Executive Committee, 5 Sep 1986 - 5 Aug 1988 (Box 2)
    - Fringe Benefits Committee, 11 Jun 1986 - 6 Jan 1993 (Box 2)
    - Governmental Relations Committee, 12 Jan 1988 - 5 Sep 1995 (Box 2)
    - IUB Professional Staff Association (Box 2)
      - 18 Feb 1982 - 30 Apr 1986 (Box 2)
      - 12 Dec 1984 - 3 Dec 1990 (Box 2)
    - IUB Professional Staff Council (Box 2)
      - Breakfast Forum Committee, 12 Jul 1995 - 15 Aug 1995 (Box 2)
      - Business Meeting (Box 2)
        - 1986 (Box 2)
        - 1987 (Box 2)
        - 1988 (Box 2)
        - 1989 (Box 2)
        - 1990 (Box 2)
        - 1991 (Box 2)
        - 1992 (Box 2)
        - 1993 (Box 2)
        - 1994 (Box 2)
        - 1995 (Box 2)
        - 17 Jan 1996 - 19 Jun 1996 (Box 2)
        - 18 Jul 1996 - 18 Dec 1996 (Box 2)
        - 15 Jan 1997 - 18 Jun 1997 (Box 2)
        - 16 Jul 1997 - 17 Dec 1997 (Box 2)
        - 21 Jan 1998 - 17 Jun 1998 (Box 3)
        - 15 Jul 1998 - 16 Dec 1998 (Box 3)
      - Executive Council, Fall 1988 (Box 3)
      - IU Professional Council News (Box 3)
        - Sep 1986 - Nov 1990 (Box 3)
        - Feb 1991 - Nov 1997 (Box 3)
      - Retreat, Aug 1992 - 1997 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Notes for Meeting Minutes, undated (Box 3)
    - Nominating Committee, 27 Oct 1986 - 12 Oct 1994 (Box 3)
    - Parliamentary Committee, 12 Nov 1990 - 15 May 1991 (Box 3)
    - Professional Affairs Committee, 18 Jul 1986 - 18 Aug 1988 (Box 3)
    - Professional Concerns Committee, 3 Sep 1990 - 18 Feb 1997 (Box 3)
    - Professional Staff Council, 11 Mar 1985 - 17 Apr 1991 (Box 3)
    - Public Relations Committee, 10 Sep 1986 - 10 Dec 1986 (Box 3)
    - Representation Committee, 17 Dec 1981 - 11 Oct 1982 (Box 3)
    - Responsibility Centered Management (RCM) Committee, 24 Oct 1994 (Box 3)
    - Salary & Benefits Committee, 20 Mar 1989 - 12 Dec 1997 (Box 3)
    - Transportation & Parking Advisory Committee & Parking Decal Subcommittee, 1 Apr 1987 - 1 Nov 1996 (Box 3)
    - Ways & Means Committee, 26 Aug 1986 - Oct 1986 (Box 3)
- Membership, 1984-1998
  - Lists, 1984-1998
    - Indiana University Professional Staff Association, May 1984 - 30 Mar 1985 (Box 3)
    - Indiana University-Bloomington Professional Staff Council, 28 Jan 1985 - 23 Apr 1997 (Box 3)
    - Professional Staff in Bloomington by Electoral Units, 25 Mar 1986 - 16 Sep 1998 (Box 3)